<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chap_dataprep">
  <chapterinfo>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="versionfile"/>
    <author>
      <firstname>Bastien</firstname>
      <surname>Chevreux</surname>
      <email>bach@chevreux.org</email>
    </author>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="copyrightfile"/>
  </chapterinfo>
  <blockquote>
    <attribution>Solomon Short</attribution>
    <para>
      <emphasis><quote>Rome didn't fall in a day either.</quote></emphasis>
    </para>
  </blockquote>
  <title>Preparing data</title>
  <sect1 id="sect_pd_introduction">
    <title>
      Introduction
    </title>
    <para>
      Most of this chapter and many sections are just stubs at the moment.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="sect_pd_sanger">
    <title>
      Sanger
    </title>
    <para>
      Outside MIRA: transform .ab1 to .scf, perform sequencing vector clip
      (and cloning vector clip if used), basic quality clips.
    </para>
    <para>
      Recommended program: <command>gap4</command> (or
      rather <command>pregap4</command>) from the Staden 4 package.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="sect_pd_454">
    <title>
      Roche / 454
    </title>
    <para>
      Outside MIRA: convert SFF instrument from Roche to FASTQ,
      use <command>sff_extract</command> for that. In case you used
      "non-standard" sequencing procedures: clip away MIDs, clip away
      non-standard sequencing adaptors used in that project.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="sect_pd_illumina">
    <title>
      Illumina
    </title>
    <para>
      Outside MIRA: for heavens' sake: do NOT try to clip or trim by quality
      yourself. Do NOT try to remove standard sequencing adaptors
      yourself. Just leave Illumina data alone! (really, I mean it).
    </para>
    <para>
      MIRA is much, much better at that job than you will probably ever be
      ... and I dare to say that MIRA is better at that job than 99% of all
      clipping/trimming software existing out there. Just make sure you use
      the <arg>-CL:pec</arg> (proposed_end_clip) option of MIRA.
    </para>
    <note>
      The <emphasis>only</emphasis> exception to the above is if you (or your
      sequencing provider) used decidedly non-standard sequencing
      adaptors. Then it might be worthwhile to perform own adaptor
      clipping. But this will not be the case for 99% of all sequencing
      projects out there.
    </note>
    <para>
      Joining paired-ends: if you want to do this, feel free to use any tool
      which is out there (TODO: quick list). Just make sure they do not join
      on very short overlaps. For me, the minimum overlap is at least 17
      bases, but I more commonly use at least 30.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="sect_pd_iontor">
    <title>
      Ion Torrent
    </title>
    <para>
      Outside MIRA: need to convert BAM to FASTQ. Need to clip away
      non-standard sequencing adaptors if used in that project. Apart from
      that: leave the data alone.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="sect_pd_sra">
    <title>
      Short Read Archive (SRA)
    </title>
    <para>
      Outside MIRA: you need to convert SRA format to FASTQ format. This is done
      using <command>fastq-dump</command> from the SRA toolkit from the
      NCBI. Make sure to have at least version 2.4.x of the toolkit. Last time
      I looked (March 2015), the software was at
      <ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Traces/sra/?view=software"/>, the
      documentation for the whole toolkit was at
      <ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Traces/sra/?view=toolkit_doc"/>,
      and for <command>fastq-dump</command> it was
      <ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Traces/sra/?view=toolkit_doc&amp;f=fastq-dump"/>
    </para>
    <para>
      After extraction, proceed with preprocessing as described above,
      depending on the sequencing technology used.
    </para>
    <para>
      For extracting Illumina data, use something like this:
    </para>
    <screen><prompt>arcadia:/some/path$</prompt> <userinput>fastq-dump -I --split-files <replaceable>somefile.sra</replaceable></userinput></screen>
    <note>
      <para>
	As <command>fastq-dump</command> unfortunately uses a pretty wasteful
	variant of the FASTQ format, you might want to reduce the file size
	for each FASTQ it produces by doing this:
      </para>
      <screen><userinput>sed -i '3~4 s/^+.*$/+/' <replaceable>file.fastq</replaceable></userinput></screen>
      <para>
	The above command performs an in-file replacement of unnecessary name
	and comments on the quality divider lines of the FASTQ. The exact
	translation of the <command>sed</command> is: do an in-file
	replacement (-i); starting on the third line, then every fourth line
	(3~4); substitute (s/); a line which starts (^); with a plus (+); and
	then can have any character (.); repeated any number of times
	including zero (*); until the end of the line ($); by just a single
	plus character (/+/).
      </para>
      <para>
	This alone reduces the file size of a typical Illumina data set with
	100mers extracted from the SRA by about 15 to 20%.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
